<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-btw-add-ipsecme-ike-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IKEv2 for Encrypted DNS">Internet Key Exchange Protocol
    Version 2 (IKEv2) Configuration for Encrypted DNS</title>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="McAfee">McAfee, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560071</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>TirumaleswarReddy_Konda@McAfee.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
      <organization abbrev="Citrix">Citrix Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dwing-ietf@fuggles.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Valery Smyslov" initials="V." surname="Smyslov">
      <organization>ELVIS-PLUS</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>RU</country>
        </postal>

        <email>svan@elvis.ru</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>ADD</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies a new Internet Key Exchange Protocol Version
      2 (IKEv2) Configuration Payload Attribute Types for encrypted DNS with a
      focus on DNS-over-HTTPS (DoH), DNS-over-TLS (DoT), and DNS-over-QUIC
      (DoQ).</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>This document specifies encrypted DNS configuration for an Internet
      Key Exchange Protocol Version 2 (IKEv2) <xref target="RFC7296"></xref>
      initiator, particularly the Authentication Domain Name (ADN, defined in
      <xref target="RFC8310"></xref>) of DNS-over-HTTPS (DoH) <xref
      target="RFC8484"></xref>, DNS-over-TLS (DoT) <xref
      target="RFC7858"></xref>, or DNS-over-QUIC (DoQ) <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsoquic"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This document introduces new IKEv2 Configuration Payload Attribute
      Types (<xref target="RI"></xref>) for the support of DoT, DoH, and DoQ
      DNS servers.</t>

      <t>This document targets the deployments discussed in Section 3.3 of
      <xref target="I-D.box-add-requirements"></xref>. Sample use cases are
      discussed in <xref target="depl"></xref>. The Configuration Payload
      Attribute Types defined in this document are not specific to these
      deployments, but can also be used in other deployment contexts.</t>

      <t>Note that, for many years, typical designs have often considered that
      the DNS server was usually located inside the protected domain, but
      could be located outside of it. With DoH, DoT, or DoQ the latter option
      becomes plausible.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref><xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <t>This document makes use of the terms defined in <xref
      target="RFC8499"></xref> and <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-terminology-ter"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Also, this document makes use of the terms defined in <xref
      target="RFC7296"></xref>. In particular, readers should be familiar with
      "initiator" and "responder" terms used in that document.</t>

      <t>Do53 refers to unencrypted DNS.</t>

      <t>Encrypted DNS refers to as scheme where DNS messages are sent over an
      encrypted channel. Examples of encrypted DNS are DoT, DoH, and DoQ.</t>

      <t>ENCDNS_IP*_* refers to any IKEv2 Configuration Payload Attribute
      Types defined in <xref target="RI"></xref>.</t>

      <t>ENCDNS_IP4_* refers to an IKEv2 Configuration Payload Attribute Type
      that carries one or multiple IPv4 addresses of an encrypted DNS
      server.</t>

      <t>ENCDNS_IP6_* refers to an IKEv2 Configuration Payload Attribute Type
      that carries one or multiple IPv6 addresses of an encrypted DNS
      server.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="depl" title="Sample Deployment Scenarios">
      <t></t>

      <section title="Roaming Enterprise Users">
        <t>In this Enterprise scenario (Section 1.1.3 of <xref
        target="RFC7296"></xref>), a roaming user connects to the Enterprise
        network through an IPsec tunnel. The split-tunnel Virtual Private
        Network (VPN) configuration allows the endpoint to access hosts that
        resides in the Enterprise network <xref target="RFC8598"></xref> using
        that tunnel; other traffic not destined to the Enterprise does not
        traverse the tunnel. In contrast, a non-split-tunnel VPN configuration
        causes all traffic to traverse the tunnel into the enterprise.</t>

        <t>For both split- and non-split-tunnel configurations, the use of
        encrypted DNS instead of Do53 provides privacy and integrity
        protection along the entire path (rather than just to the VPN
        termination device) and can communicate the encrypted DNS server
        policies.</t>

        <t>For split-tunnel VPN configurations, the endpoint uses the
        Enterprise-provided encrypted DNS server to resolve internal-only
        domain names.</t>

        <t>For non-split-tunnel VPN configurations, the endpoint uses the
        Enterprise-provided encrypted DNS server to resolve both internal and
        external domain names.</t>

        <t>Enterprise networks are susceptible to internal and external
        attacks. To minimize that risk all enterprise traffic is encrypted
        (Section 2.1 of <xref
        target="I-D.arkko-farrell-arch-model-t"></xref>).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="VPN Service Provider">
        <t>Legacy VPN service providers usually preserve end-users' data
        confidentiality by sending all communication traffic through an
        encrypted tunnel. A VPN service provider can also provide guarantees
        about the security of the VPN network by filtering malware and
        phishing domains.</t>

        <t>Browsers and OSes support DoH/DoT; VPN providers may no longer
        expect DNS clients to fallback to Do53 just because it is a closed
        network.</t>

        <t>The encrypted DNS server hosted by the VPN service provider can be
        securely discovered by the endpoint using the IKEv2 Configuration
        Payload Attribute Type.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="DNS Offload">
        <t>VPN service providers typically allow split-tunnel VPN
        configuration in which users can choose applications that can be
        excluded from the tunnel. For example, users may exclude applications
        that restrict VPN access.</t>

        <t>The encrypted DNS server hosted by the VPN service provider can be
        securely discovered by the endpoint using the IKEv2 Configuration
        Payload Attribute Type.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="RI"
             title="IKEv2 Configuration Payload Attribute Types for Encrypted DNS">
      <t>The ENCDNS_IP*_* IKEv2 Configuration Payload Attribute Types are used
      to configure a DoT, DoH, or DoQ DNS server. All these attributes share
      the format shown in <xref target="ri_attr"></xref>.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="ri_attr" title="Attributes Format">
          <artwork><![CDATA[                     1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-----------------------------+-------------------------------+
|R|         Attribute Type      |            Length             |
+-+-----------------------------+---------------+---------------+
|          Port Number          |    RESERVED   | Num Addresses |
+-------------------------------+---------------+---------------+
|                                                               | 
~                         IP Addresses                          ~
|                                                               |
+---------------------------------------------------------------+
|                                                               |
~                  DNS Authentication Domain Name               ~
|                                                               |
+---------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The fields of the attribute shown in <xref target="ri_attr"></xref>
      are as follows:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>R (Reserved, 1 bit) - This bit MUST be set to zero and MUST be
          ignored on receipt (see Section 3.15.1 of <xref
          target="RFC7296"></xref> for details).</t>

          <t>Attribute Type (15 bits) - Identifier for Configuration Attribute
          Type; is set to one of the values listed in <xref
          target="IANA1"></xref>.</t>

          <t>Length (2 octets, unsigned integer) - Length of the data in
          octets. In particular, this field is set to:<list style="symbols">
              <t>0 if the Configuration payload has types CFG_REQUEST or
              CFG_ACK.</t>

              <t>(2 + Length of the ADN + N * 4) for ENCDNS_IP4_* attributes
              if the Configuration payload of a has types CFG_REPLY or
              CFG_SET; N being the number of included IPv4 addresses ('Num
              addresses').</t>

              <t>(2 + Length of the ADN + N * 16) for ENCDNS_IP6_* attributes
              if the Configuration payload has types CFG_REPLY or CFG_SET; N
              being the number of included IPv6 addresses ('Num
              addresses').</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Port Number (2 octets, unsigned integer) - Indicates the port
          number to be used for the encrypted DNS. As a reminder, the default
          port number is 853 for DoT and 443 for DoH.</t>

          <t>RESERVED (1 octet) - These bits are reserved for future use.
          These bits MUST be set to zero by the sender and MUST be ignored by
          the receiver.</t>

          <t>Num Addresses (1 octet) - Indicates the number of enclosed IPv4
          (for ENCDNS_IP4_* attribute types) or IPv6 (for ENCDNS_IP6_*
          attribute types) addresses.</t>

          <t>IP Address(es) (variable) - One or more IPv4 or IPv6 addresses to
          be used to reach the encrypted DNS identified by the name in the DNS
          Authentication Domain Name.</t>

          <t>Authentication Domain Name (variable) - A fully qualified domain
          name of the DoT, DoH, or DoQ DNS server following the syntax defined
          in <xref target="RFC5890"></xref>. The name MUST NOT contain any
          terminators (e.g., NULL, CR). <vspace blankLines="1" />An example of
          valid ADN for DoH server is "doh1.example.com".</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="protocol" title="IKEv2 Protocol Exchange">
      <t>This section describes how an initiator can be configured with an
      encrypted DNS server (e.g., DoH, DoT) using IKEv2.</t>

      <t>Initiators indicate the support of an encrypted DNS in the
      CFG_REQUEST payloads by including one or multiple ENCDNS_IP*_*
      attributes, while responders supply the encrypted DNS configuration in
      the CFG_REPLY payloads. Concretely:</t>

      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>If the initiator supports encrypted DNS, it includes one or more
          ENCDNS_IP*_* attributes in the CFG_REQUEST with the "Attribute Type"
          set to the requested encrypted DNS type (<xref target="RI"></xref>).
          For each supported encrypted DNS type the initiator MUST include
          exactly one attribute with the Length field set to 0, so that no
          data is included for these attributes.</t>

          <t>For each ENCDNS_IP*_* attribute from the CFG_REQUEST, if the
          responder supports the corresponding encrypted DNS type, and absent
          any policy, the responder sends back an ENCDNS_IP*_* attribute in
          the CFG_REPLY with this encrypted DNS type and an appropriate list
          of IP addresses, a port number, and an ADN. The list of IP addresses
          MUST NOT be empty. Multiple instances of the same ENCDNS_IP*_*
          attribute MAY be returned if distinct ADNs (or port numbers) are to
          be returned by the responder.</t>

          <t>If the CFG_REQUEST includes an ENCDNS_IP*_* attribute but the
          CFG_REPLY does not include an ENCDNS_IP*_* matching the requested
          encrypted DNS type, this is an indication that requested encrypted
          DNS type(s) is not supported by the responder or the responder is
          not configured to provide corresponding server addresses.</t>

          <t>The behavior of the responder if it receives both ENCDNS_IP*_*
          and INTERNAL_IP6_DNS (or INTERNAL_IP4_DNS) attributes is
          policy-based and deployment-specific. However, it is RECOMMENDED
          that if the responder includes at least one ENCDNS_IP*_* attribute
          in the reply, it should not include any of
          INTERNAL_IP4_DNS/INTERNAL_IP6_DNS attributes.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The DNS client establishes an encrypted DNS session (e.g., DoT, DoH,
      DoQ) with the address(es) conveyed in ENCDNS_IP*_* and uses the
      mechanism discussed in Section 8 of <xref target="RFC8310"></xref> to
      authenticate the DNS server certificate using the authentication domain
      name conveyed in ENCDNS_IP*_*.</t>

      <t>If the IPsec connection is a split-tunnel configuration and the
      initiator negotiated INTERNAL_DNS_DOMAIN as per <xref
      target="RFC8598"></xref>, the DNS client MUST resolve the internal names
      using ENCDNS_IP*_* DNS servers.</t>

      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>Note: <xref target="RFC8598"></xref> requires INTERNAL_IP6_DNS
          (or INTERNAL_IP4_DNS) attribute to be mandatory present when
          INTERNAL_DNS_DOMAIN is included. This specification relaxes that
          constraint in the presence of ENCDNS_IP*_* attributes.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="URI Template">
      <t>DoH servers may support more than one URI Template <xref
      target="RFC8484"></xref>. Also, if the resolver hosts several DoH
      services (e.g., no-filtering, blocking adult content, blocking malware),
      these services can be discovered as templates.</t>

      <t>Upon discovery of a DoH resolver (<xref target="protocol"></xref>),
      the DoH client contacts that DoH resolver to retrieve the list of
      supported DoH services using the well-known URI defined in <xref
      target="I-D.btw-add-rfc8484-clarification"></xref>. DoH clients
      re-iterates that request regularly to retrieve an updated list of
      supported DoH services.</t>

      <t>How a DoH client makes use of the configured DoH services is out of
      the scope of this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document adheres to the security considerations defined in <xref
      target="RFC7296"></xref>. In particular, this document does not alter
      the trust on the DNS configuration provided by a responder.</t>

      <t>Networks are susceptible to internal attacks as discussed in Section
      3.2 of <xref target="I-D.arkko-farrell-arch-model-t"></xref>. Hosting
      encrypted DNS server even in case of split-VPN configuration minimizes
      the attack vector (e.g., a compromised network device cannot
      monitor/modify DNS traffic). This specification describes a mechanism to
      restrict access to the DNS messages to only the parties that need to
      know.</t>

      <t>In most deployment scenarios, the initiator expects that it is using
      the encrypted DNS server hosted by a specific organization or
      enterprise. The DNS client can validate the signatory (i.e.,
      cryptographically attested by the organization hosting the encrypted DNS
      server) using, for example, <xref
      target="I-D.reddy-add-server-policy-selection"></xref>, and the user can
      review human-readable privacy policy information of the DNS server and
      assess whether the DNS server performs DNS-based content filtering. This
      helps to protect from a compromised IKE server advertising a malicious
      encrypted DNS server.</t>

      <t>The initiator may trust the encrypted DNS servers supplied by means
      of IKEv2 from a trusted responder more than the locally provided DNS
      servers, especially in the case of connecting to unknown or untrusted
      networks (e.g., coffee shops or hotel networks). </t>

      <t>If the encrypted DNS server that was discovered by means of IKEv2
      does not meet the privacy preserving data policy and filtering
      requirements of the user, the user can instruct the DNS client to take
      appropriate actions. For example, the action can be to use the local
      encrypted DNS server only to access internal-only DNS names and use
      another DNS server (that addresses his/her expectations) for public
      domains. Such actions and their handling is out of scope.</t>

      <t>If IKEv2 responder has used NULL Authentication method <xref
      target="RFC7619"></xref> to authenticate itself, the initiator MUST NOT
      use returned ENCDNS_IP*_* servers configuration unless it is
      pre-configured in the OS or the browser.</t>

      <t>This specification does not extend the scope of accepting DNSSEC
      trust anchors beyond the usage guidelines defined in Section 6 of <xref
      target="RFC8598"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t></t>

      <section anchor="IANA1" title="Configuration Payload Attribute Types">
        <t>This document requests IANA to assign the following new IKEv2
        Configuration Payload Attribute Types from the "IKEv2 Configuration
        Payload Attribute Types" namespace available at
        https://www.iana.org/assignments/ikev2-parameters/ikev2-parameters.xhtml#ikev2-parameters-21.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[                                 Multi-
   Value    Attribute Type       Valued  Length      Reference
   ------   -------------------  ------  ----------  ------------
   TBA1      ENCDNS_IP4_DOT        YES   0 or more   RFC XXXX
   TBA2      ENCDNS_IP6_DOT        YES   0 or more   RFC XXXX
   TBA3      ENCDNS_IP4_DOH        YES   0 or more   RFC XXXX
   TBA4      ENCDNS_IP6_DOH        YES   0 or more   RFC XXXX
   TBA5      ENCDNS_IP4_DOQ        YES   0 or more   RFC XXXX
   TBA6      ENCDNS_IP6_DOQ        YES   0 or more   RFC XXXX
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Many thanks to Yoav Nir, Christian Jacquenet, Paul Wouters, and Tommy
      Pauly for the review and comments.</t>

      <t>Yoav and Paul suggested the use of one single attribute carrying both
      the name and an IP address instead of depending on the existing
      INTERNAL_IP6_DNS and INTERNAL_IP4_DNS attributes.</t>

      <t>Christian Huitema suiggested to return a port number in the
      attributes.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7296'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8310'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5890'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8499'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.box-add-requirements'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7858'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsoquic'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8484'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8598'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-terminology-ter'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.arkko-farrell-arch-model-t'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7619'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.reddy-add-server-policy-selection'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.btw-add-rfc8484-clarification'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
